Guide to the David John Lewis Papers, 1894-1949 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
David John Lewis papers 1894-1949 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lewis, David John
4.4 linear feet Extent: 3,294 Items
Lawyer, member of U.S. Tariff Commission, and U.S. Representative from Maryland. Letters, political and professional papers, scrapbooks, and newspaper clippings reflecting Lewis' interest in free trade and his effort to unseat Senator Millard Tydings of Maryland in 1938.
lewisdavidjohn
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The David John Lewis Papers were received as a gift by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1954.
Collection Overview
Papers of David John Lewis (1869-1952), lawyer and U.S. representative from Maryland, 1910-1916 and 1930-1939; member of the U.S. Tariff Commission, 1916-1925; and member of the National Mediation Board, 1939-1943. Included are recommendations for Lewis' appointment to the tariff commission as the choice of free trade interests, 1916; and letters, 1917-1925, relating to the collection of data on costs of production and productive capability in the United States. A later series of tariff letters, 1929-1930, include some from William Thomas Rawleigh, spice and extract manufacturer and free trader; other letters concern the Hawley-Smoot tariff of 1929 and deal with proposed rates for many types of products. Papers relating to the tariff, 1910-1950, largely reflect the period when Lewis was special consultant to the Rawleigh Tariff Bureau, 1925-1930, including notes, reports, statistics, Congressional prints, voting records of Congressmen, and memoranda. They concern proposed rates for many types of goods and contain information about the productive capacity of American industry and the cost of production. Scattered throughout the collection are miscellaneous letters concerning politics and Lewis's political career. Letters from the 1940s concern international relations and the Senate's treaty powers. There are also letters, legal documents, and other papers relating to a lawsuit against the Cumberland, Maryland, water department, 1925-1948. Some World War II letters from Lewis' Welsh relatives describe the hardships of life in Great Britain. After 1943 there are letters relating to spiritualism, especially concerning the work of such organizations as the Society for Psychical Research in London, the American Society for Psychical Research, New York; and the Duke University Parapsychology Laboratory. Printed materials accompanying the collection include Congressional reports, hearings, speeches, newspaper clippings, press releases, publications of the Rawleigh Tariff Bureau, and election campaign material. Scrapbooks, 12 vols., contain letters from prominent individuals, clippings concerning Lewis' career and his unsuccessful campaign for the U.S. Senate in 1938.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Lewis, John David; Tydings, Millard E. (Millard Evelyn), 1890-1961; Free trade; Legislators -- Virginia -- Correspondence; Maryland -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Tariffs -- United States -- History; Rawleigh Tariff Bureau
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1905-1949 and undated, (2 boxes)
  - 1905-1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1949 and undated (Box 2)
- Political and Professional Papers Series, 1894-1945 and undated, (15 boxes)
  - Tariff papers and rates
    - Cotton (Box 3)
    - Rayon
    - Silk
    - Wool
    - Scientific and medical instruments (Box 4)
    - Sundries
    - Buttons
    - Clothing
    - Five and ten cent articles
    - Bricks (Box 5)
    - Chemicals
    - Marble iron
    - Granite
    - Explosives
    - Boots and shoes
    - Leather gloves
    - Cattle (Box 6)
    - Agricultural products
    - Farm machinery
    - Linseed oil
    - Furniture
    - Lumber
    - Cement (Box 7)
    - Glass
    - Pottery
    - Books (Box 8)
    - Watches
    - Razors
    - Toys and dolls
    - Ropes and cordage
    - Carpets and rugs
    - Sugar (Box 9)
    - General (Box 10-11)
    - Miscellany (Box 11)
    - Printed Material
  - Legislative Papers (Box 12)
  - Walter Case Papers
    - Correspondence (Box 13)
    - Financial Papers
    - Printed Materials
    - Legal Papers (Box 14)
  - Financial Papers (Box 15)
  - Speeches, 1894-1945 and undated (Box 16-17)
- Photographs Series, (1 box)
  - Photographs (Box 18)
- Printed Material Series, 1906-1940s and undated, (5 boxes)
  - Miscellany (Box 18)
  - Clippings, 1906-1933 (Box 19)
  - Clippings, 1934-1940s and undated (Box 20)
  - Other Printed Material (Box 21-22)
- Volumes, (3 boxes)
  - Volumes (Box 23-24)
  - Volumes, scrapbooks (Box 25)